<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving
and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">

<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">

<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>

<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Center for Democracy and Civic Engagement, University of
Maryland</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>

<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>


<article-meta>


<title-group>
<article-title>Psychological Empowerment and Turnover: A Review of the
Literature</article-title>
</title-group>

<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Espinoza</surname>
<given-names>Isaiah</given-names>
</name>
<string-name>Isaiah Espinoza</string-name>
<degrees>Research Assistant</degrees>
<email>gespinoz@umd.edu</email>
<role>Research Assistant</role>
<role>Reviewer</role>
<role>Analyst</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1">a</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-2">b</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff-1">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>Center for Democracy and Civic Engagement</institution>
</institution-wrap>







</aff>
<aff id="aff-2">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>University of Maryland at College Park</institution>
</institution-wrap>







</aff>

<pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic" iso-8601-date="2024-04-22">
<year>2024</year>
<month>4</month>
<day>22</day>
</pub-date>







<history></history>


<abstract>
<p>An increase in turnover among the election administration workforce
has been observed and become recently salient. Election administration
work (e.g., poll workers) is certainly difficult. The impetus of the
following review was to discover what lessons, supports, or specific
interventions could be derived from selected literature to potentially
help reduce turnover, turnover intention, and boost morale for election
workers in particular. A selection of academic literature on
psychological empowerment and turnover are reviewed for that
purpose.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
<kwd>Psychological Empowerment</kwd>
<kwd>Turnover</kwd>
<kwd>Election resiliency</kwd>
<kwd>Poll workers</kwd>
<kwd>Election administration</kwd>
</kwd-group>




</article-meta>

</front>

<body>
<sec id="introduction">
  <title>Introduction</title>
  <p>Psychological empowerment has been studied extensively within
  organizational psychology and management studies with the aim of
  determining drivers for workplace performance and retention.
  Researchers of the field were interested in understanding how workers
  adapt and adjust to work environments, what motivates workers to go
  above and beyond minimal workplace performance, and what might
  decrease the likelihood of turnover. The reason for the interest in
  the individual psychology of the worker was seemingly prompted by the
  limitations of previous research up to that point. Prior to the shift
  toward the psychological, research was limited to classical
  bureaucratic explanations of how workplace performance and
  satisfaction was best improved. That is, work was assumed to have only
  <italic>instrumental value</italic> to the workers. As such,
  performance, retention, and workplace satisfaction was determined
  through different organizational controls in combination with
  contingent rewards and punishments. As will be seen, some researchers
  saw this tradition as limiting and were thus motivated to determine
  and study those organizational structures and workplace interventions
  that have the most empowering effects on the individual workers
  themselves. This branch of research introduced a novel paradigm
  exploring the significance of a worker’s <italic>internalized
  commitment</italic> to the work itself in order to understand and help
  to foster worker empowerment
  (<xref alt="Thomas and Velthouse 1990" rid="ref-thomas1990" ref-type="bibr">Thomas
  and Velthouse 1990</xref>). In other words, the degree to which a
  worker was <italic>intrinsically motivated</italic> to do their work
  became a much more prominent focus for interested researchers.</p>
  <p>Drawing upon and contributing to the burgeoning psychology research
  on motivation in the later half of the 1980s and early 1990s, a
  prominent concept to emerge was <italic>psychological
  empowerment</italic>, which was theorized to be a multidimensional
  concept manifested as a set of four distinguished ‘cognitions’:
  <italic>meaning</italic>, <italic>competence</italic>,
  <italic>self-determination</italic>, and <italic>impact</italic>. The
  Psychological Empowerment Scale was later developed, tested, and
  applied in multiple studies inquiring into whether it served as a
  mediator for certain workplace behaviors and turnover intention.</p>
  <p>The concerted focus in the psychological empowerment literature on
  individual differences between workers’ feelings of empowerment,
  however, isn’t able to offer much in terms of how to improve
  psychological empowerment among workers in general. Although some
  recommendations are offered, it is difficult to recommend general
  “one-size-fits-all” solutions to increase psychological empowerment
  for individual workers or an entire workforce. Seeing as how
  individual people are quite different in terms of what motivates them,
  provides meaning, makes them feel competent, and so on, the reviewed
  literature is limited in that respect. As will be seen, for instance,
  one strategy to improve empowerment is to change the way the workers
  interpret the information gleaned from their workplace environment and
  outcomes
  (<xref alt="Thomas and Velthouse 1990" rid="ref-thomas1990" ref-type="bibr">Thomas
  and Velthouse 1990</xref>).</p>
  <p>The academic literature examining turnover intention provides a
  contrast to the research focused on psychological empowerment.
  Research on retention and turnover has tended to focus primarily on
  the workplace context and organizational factors that influence a
  workers job satisfaction and organizational commitment. Although
  empowerment is often included as a factor within this line of
  research, the focus is less concerned with individual level psychology
  and more concerned with factors such as quality of pay, benefits,
  advancement opportunities and the like. There are a few recommended
  intervention strategies to improve retention, but pertain more toward
  shaping a friendly, inclusive, and beneficial workplace
  environment.</p>
  <p>This review summarizes a selection of the literature on the
  concept, measurement, and examination of psychological empowerment as
  it influences workplace behavior and worker attitudes. Also reviewed
  are the interventions suggested which aim to reduce turnover, increase
  empowerment, workplace satisfaction, and improve worker
  performance.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="psychological-empowerment-theory-and-measurement">
  <title>Psychological Empowerment: theory and measurement</title>
  <sec id="powerlessness-in-the-workplace">
    <title>Powerlessness in the workplace</title>
    <p>Initially, the idea of <italic>powerlessness</italic> in the
    workplace referred to feeling a lack of autonomy and influence in
    the workplace
    (<xref alt="Ashforth 1989" rid="ref-ashforth1989" ref-type="bibr">Ashforth
    1989</xref>). Autonomy was generally understood as, “The degree to
    which the job provides substantial freedom, independence, and
    discretion to the employee in scheduling his work and in determining
    the procedures to be used in carrying it out”
    (<xref alt="Hackman and Oldham 1975" rid="ref-hackman1975" ref-type="bibr">Hackman
    and Oldham 1975</xref>). Ashforth
    (<xref alt="1989" rid="ref-ashforth1989" ref-type="bibr">1989</xref>)
    argued that feelings of powerlessness were incurred from unmet
    expectations and desires of personal autonomy and involvement in the
    workplace. His argument was that the greater the difference between
    expectations and perception of reality in the workplace generates
    feelings of powerlessness. Such powerlessness kicks off a contrived
    process of psychological adjustment and coping. People first react
    to the difference between expectations and reality, then develop
    increased feelings of inability to improve their situation (i.e.,
    helplessness) based on the realities of their experience at work.
    Then, finally, come to feel detached and alienated from the job and
    organization entirely.</p>
    <disp-quote>
      <p>“The findings, then, suggest that powerlessness and high
      generalized expectations of
      control<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1">1</xref> give rise to unmet
      expectations/desires for control; that the latter two constructs
      fuel reactance; that reactance in turn, along with powerlessness,
      increases helplessness; and that helplessness increases work
      alienation. The model suggests that the experience of
      powerlessness can be quite traumatic, entailing frustration,
      disruptive behaviors, feelings of helplessness, and loss of job
      involvement and organizational identification. Conversely, it
      suggests that fostering a sense of control can forestall
      frustration and reactance, increase perceptions of organizational
      legitimacy and self-efficacy, and stimulate involvement.”
      (<xref alt="Ashforth 1989, 234" rid="ref-ashforth1989" ref-type="bibr">Ashforth
      1989, 234</xref>)</p>
    </disp-quote>
    <sec id="recommended-interventions">
      <title>Recommended Interventions</title>
      <p>The recommended interventions of this early study were simple
      and intuitive: make clear the actual link between the actions
      workers take and the resulting outcomes they can expect to see in
      order to increase perceptions of personal autonomy and control
      over workplace outcomes. To this end, “…provide realistic job
      previews, specific and challenging goals, prompt and balanced
      feedback, contingent reinforcement, and appropriate role models…”,
      and remove obstacles which impede personal control
      (<xref alt="Ashforth 1989, 234" rid="ref-ashforth1989" ref-type="bibr">Ashforth
      1989, 234</xref>). In addition, it was suggested that management
      relax or delegate control to those workers whose jobs hold less
      actual influence or significance. By providing opportunities for
      workers with “low power jobs” to participate in the strategic and
      operational decisions usually confined to managerial roles,
      workers may come to feel as though their input is not only valued
      but influential upon the final decisions
      made<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2">2</xref>. Although the reported
      findings of Ashforth
      (<xref alt="1989" rid="ref-ashforth1989" ref-type="bibr">1989</xref>)’s
      study were narratively intuitive, and the interventions sensible,
      it is unclear whether the theoretical process of powerlessness
      results in powerlessness or begins from
      it<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn3">3</xref>.</p>
    </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec id="the-interpretive-model-of-empowerment">
    <title>The Interpretive Model of Empowerment</title>
    <p>The difficulties and limitations of prior research prompted later
    researchers to refine a more cohesive theoretical model of
    empowerment. The publication by Thomas and Velthouse
    (<xref alt="1990" rid="ref-thomas1990" ref-type="bibr">1990</xref>)
    elaborates on a theoretical model of empowerment based on review of
    relevant literature (up to the point of publication in
    1990)<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn4">4</xref>. These authors
    conceptualized empowerment as a multidimensional concept and
    operationalized empowerment as <italic>intrinsic task
    motivation</italic>, which refers to positive experiences derived
    directly from doing some task. The cognitive model developed
    involves identifying certain cognitions, referred to as <italic>task
    assessments</italic>, which manifests as a set of four cognitions
    reflecting an individual’s orientation to their task/work role:
    <italic>meaning</italic>, <italic>competence</italic>,
    <italic>self-determination</italic>, and <italic>impact</italic>.
    These task assessments are assumed to be the “proximal cause” of
    intrinsic task motivation. That is to say, these four “cognitions”
    are considered latent constructs of their own, which in turn
    manifest the second-order latent construct
    empowerment<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn5">5</xref>.</p>
    <p>An assumption of the conceptual definition of empowerment is that
    it is not understood as an enduring personality trait generalizable
    across situations. The set of four cognitions, i.e., task
    assessments, are said to be shaped by the work environment. This
    fixes empowerment to the specific workplace domain.</p>
    <p>To put the theory in brief: People are empowered (i.e.,
    energized) when they are <italic>intrinsically motivated</italic> to
    carry out some task, and they feel <italic>intrinsically
    motivated</italic> when they 1) judge the tasks as sufficiently
    <italic>impactful</italic> (i.e., the degree to which behavior is
    seen as making a difference in terms of accomplishing the purpose of
    the task), 2) judge themselves as <italic>competent</italic> (i.e.,
    self-efficacy), 3) find the task <italic>meaningful</italic>, and 4)
    feel as though their decision to do the task is
    <italic>self-determined</italic> (i.e., autonomous). They come to
    judge specific tasks in this way by their particular kind of
    <italic>interpretive style</italic> and <italic>global
    beliefs</italic> about work in general as information is gleaned
    from event outcomes observed in the workplace environment. That is
    to say, they interpret information from the outcomes in whatever way
    is concordant to their interpretive style and “global assessments”
    of tasks. When their interpretation of the outcomes leads to higher
    task assessments (i.e., higher values of the four cognitive
    variables), they then feel <italic>intrinsically</italic> motivated
    to carry out the task, resulting in behaviors in which they may
    demonstrate <italic>flexibility</italic>,
    <italic>initiative</italic>, and <italic>resilience</italic>. Such
    behavioral outcomes are attributed purely to the authors’ theory on
    the effects of the four components of “intrinsic task
    motivation”.</p>
    <p>Ultimately, this theory uses the word “intrinsic” when it is
    unnecessary and not aligned with its meaning. The authors could
    remove the word “intrinsic” entirely and it would make no
    difference; they confuse what intrinsic motivation means and don’t
    properly distinguish it from extrinsic motivation. In so doing, this
    early work is undermined by logical inconsistency. Supposing that a
    person’s motivation to do some task is indeed
    <italic>intrinsic</italic>, then information on outcomes in the
    environment should make little to no difference because the person
    is motivated <italic>to do the task itself</italic>. If the
    prospective outcome drives the individual behavior, then the
    motivation is instrumental, thus <italic>extrinsic</italic>. There’s
    a vast literature on the psychology of motivation with multiple and
    competing perspectives, especially with regard to notions of
    ‘intrinsic’ v. ‘extrinsic’ motives
    (<xref alt="Deci and Ryan 2012" rid="ref-deci2012" ref-type="bibr">Deci
    and Ryan 2012</xref>;
    <xref alt="Ryan and Deci 2000" rid="ref-ryan2000" ref-type="bibr">Ryan
    and Deci 2000</xref>,
    <xref alt="2017" rid="ref-ryan2017" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>,
    <xref alt="2021" rid="ref-ryan2021" ref-type="bibr">2021</xref>; for
    contrast, see
    <xref alt="Kruglanski et al. 2017" rid="ref-kruglanski2017" ref-type="bibr">Kruglanski
    et al. 2017</xref>; and
    <xref alt="Kruglanski et al. 2022" rid="ref-kruglanski2022" ref-type="bibr">Kruglanski
    et al. 2022</xref>).</p>
    <p>Psychological theories vary considerably in explanations of
    behavior, especially classics, whereas one theory maintains that all
    behaviors are motivated by rewards (see <italic>operant
    theory</italic>,
    <xref alt="Skinner 1965" rid="ref-skinner1965" ref-type="bibr">Skinner
    1965</xref>), another asserts that all behaviors are motivated by
    physiological drives, to which intrinsically motivated behaviors
    were ones that provided satisfaction of psychological needs
    (<xref alt="Hull 1943" rid="ref-hull1943" ref-type="bibr">Hull
    1943</xref>). More recent explanations of behavior still vary
    considerably, although a relatively recent Self-Determination Theory
    follows motivational theories to which behavior seeks to satisfy
    psychological needs
    (<xref alt="Ryan and Deci 2000" rid="ref-ryan2000" ref-type="bibr">Ryan
    and Deci 2000</xref>). In this work, <italic>intrinsic
    motivation</italic> refers to doing something because the activity
    is inherently interesting or enjoyable itself; whereas doing
    something because it leads to some separable outcome refers to
    <italic>extrinsic motivation</italic>. Although, the distinction
    isn’t necessarily as simple due to the fact that the classifying
    criteria for a behavior to be motivated intrinsically (opposed to
    extrinsically) is quite high and generally excludes many every-day
    behaviors. Ryan and Deci
    (<xref alt="2000" rid="ref-ryan2000" ref-type="bibr">2000</xref>),
    the progenitors of Self-Determination Theory proposed that the need
    for competence underlies all motivation, but full autonomy must be
    experienced for an activity to be truly intrinsically
    motivated<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn6">6</xref>.</p>
    <sec id="recommended-interventions-1">
      <title>Recommended Interventions</title>
      <p>Two different kinds of interventions are thought to increase
      empowerment (i.e., intrinsic task motivation): either adjust the
      working environment outcomes (i.e., environmental changes) or
      re-frame how environment outcomes are interpreted by individual
      workers (i.e., interpretive intervention strategies). The
      <italic>environmental changes</italic> intervention strategy
      relates to the ideas of prior research which professes that
      interventions modifying external variables such as organizational
      structure, managerial strategies, and types of information all
      work as interventions to produce increased feelings of
      empowerment. Thomas and Velthouse
      (<xref alt="1990" rid="ref-thomas1990" ref-type="bibr">1990</xref>)
      list a few environmental variables which they theorized would
      shape the four cognitions/task assessments: leadership,
      delegation, job design, and reward systems
      (<xref alt="Thomas and Velthouse 1990" rid="ref-thomas1990" ref-type="bibr">Thomas
      and Velthouse 1990</xref>, see Table 1 on page 676).</p>
      <p>The latter “<italic>interpretive intervention
      strategies</italic>” are aimed at addressing/modifying how
      individual workers construe work outcomes and consequences to
      increase worker empowerment. Only one “interpretive intervention
      strategy” is mentioned as a feasible solution according to the
      model: self-empowerment programs. Such programs are thought to
      help individuals identify and practice styles theoretically
      conducive to enhance tasks assessments crucial to increasing
      empowerment. The authors say, “The interpretive styles in the
      model are viewed as developed <italic>habits</italic> rather than
      innate abilities. These habits are relatively isolated from
      day-to-day learning activities”
      (<xref alt="Thomas and Velthouse 1990, 677" rid="ref-thomas1990" ref-type="bibr">Thomas
      and Velthouse 1990, 677</xref>, emphasis original). They go on to
      say,</p>
      <disp-quote>
        <p>“…researchers/clinicians have demonstrated that such styles
        can be changed by making the individual aware of assumptions
        that are inherent in a style and by teaching individuals to
        consciously monitor those ongoing interpretations and their
        consequences…Thus, according to the model,”self-empowerment”
        programs are feasible solutions to help individuals identify and
        practice styles of attributing, evaluating, and envisioning,
        which would enhance their task assessments.”
        (<xref alt="Thomas and Velthouse 1990, 677" rid="ref-thomas1990" ref-type="bibr">Thomas
        and Velthouse 1990, 677</xref>)</p>
      </disp-quote>
      <p>The authors don’t detail what these self-empowerment programs
      look like, but the goal is essentially to change the way the
      worker interprets the things that happen at work in order to make
      such outcomes more empowering. Offering support to the theoretical
      claims posited, the authors cite to unpublished
      work<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn7">7</xref> in which the four
      cognition task assessments of the empowerment model mediated the
      relationship between positive feedback and self-reports of
      intrinsic motivation. In other words, <italic>positive
      feedback</italic> supposedly caused increases in the four
      cognitive task assessments (e.g., meaning, competence,
      self-determination, and impact) which, in turn, increased
      self-reported ratings of intrinsic motivation
      (<xref alt="Thomas and Velthouse 1990, 677" rid="ref-thomas1990" ref-type="bibr">Thomas
      and Velthouse 1990, 677</xref>). However, it is not clear how the
      four components of empowerment were measured. Development of a
      survey measurement instrument didn’t come about until about five
      years after the model was theorized.</p>
    </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec id="psychological-empowerment-scale">
    <title>Psychological Empowerment Scale</title>
    <p>The theoretical model existed for some time before an attempt was
    made to develop a measure of psychological empowerment. Spreitzer
    (<xref alt="1995" rid="ref-spreitzer1995" ref-type="bibr">1995</xref>)
    developed and tested the validity of a novel measure of
    psychological empowerment, following the cognitive model of
    empowerment (i.e., “intrinsic task motivation”) theorized by Thomas
    and Velthouse
    (<xref alt="1990" rid="ref-thomas1990" ref-type="bibr">1990</xref>)
    and based on measurement scales adapted from previous research.</p>
    <disp-quote>
      <p>“In sum, psychological empowerment is defined as a motivational
      construct manifested in four cognitions: meaning, competence,
      self-determination, and impact. Together, these four cognitions
      reflect an active, rather than a passive, orientation to a work
      role. By active orientation, I mean an orientation in which an
      individual wishes and feels able to shape his or her work role and
      context. The four dimensions are argued to combine additively to
      create an overall construct of psychological empowerment. In other
      words, the lack of any single dimension will deflate, though not
      completely eliminate, the overall degree of felt empowerment.”
      (<xref alt="Spreitzer 1995, 1444" rid="ref-spreitzer1995" ref-type="bibr">Spreitzer
      1995, 1444</xref>)</p>
    </disp-quote>
    <p>The scale includes 12-items with the component dimensions
    measured with three items each. In this case, psychological
    empowerment is understood as a common second-order latent factor
    that underlies the four latent component factors (e.g., meaning,
    impact, competence,
    self-determination)<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn8">8</xref>.</p>
    <fig id="tbl-empowerment">
      <caption><p>Table 1: Psychological Empowerment 12-item Measurement
      scale
      (<xref alt="Spreitzer 1995" rid="ref-spreitzer1995" ref-type="bibr">Spreitzer
      1995</xref>)</p></caption>
      <table-wrap>
        <table>
          <colgroup>
            <col width="19%" />
            <col width="81%" />
          </colgroup>
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th>Component</th>
              <th align="left">Item wording</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td>Meaning</td>
              <td align="left"><list list-type="bullet">
                <list-item>
                  <p>The work I do is very important to me.</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p>My job activities are personally meaningful to
                  me.</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p>The work I do is meaningful to me.</p>
                </list-item>
              </list></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>Competence</td>
              <td align="left"><list list-type="bullet">
                <list-item>
                  <p>I am confident about my ability to do my job.</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p>I am self-assured about my capabilities to perform
                  my work activities.</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p>I have mastered the skills necessary for my
                  job.</p>
                </list-item>
              </list></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>Self-Determination</td>
              <td align="left"><list list-type="bullet">
                <list-item>
                  <p>I have significant autonomy in determining how I do
                  my job.</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p>I can decide on my own how to go about doing my
                  work.</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p>I have considerable opportunity for independence
                  and freedom in how I do my job.</p>
                </list-item>
              </list></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>Impact</td>
              <td align="left"><list list-type="bullet">
                <list-item>
                  <p>My impact on what happens in my department is
                  large.</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p>I have a great deal of control over what hap pens
                  in my department.</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p>I have significant influence over what happens in
                  my department.</p>
                </list-item>
              </list></td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </table-wrap>
    </fig>
    <p>Overall, the development and test for the original measurement
    scale for psychological empowerment can be viewed as a first step
    towards measuring empowerment in a work related context. However, no
    real useful measurement instrument for psychological empowerment is
    made readily available from this study. The methods used to test
    validity and reliability of the four measurement scales for
    empowerment is interesting but complex, and doesn’t appear to result
    in an actual estimate of the latent construct for empowerment
    itself. Instead, convergent validity is obtained but not
    discriminant validity for the four components of empowerment.
    Interested researchers might be better off developing and validating
    a single measurement scale for empowerment itself rather than rely
    on measuring the presence of four separate latent component
    constructs with 12 requisite survey items.</p>
  </sec>
</sec>
<sec id="psychological-empowerment-as-a-mediator">
  <title>Psychological Empowerment as a Mediator</title>
  <p>Multiple subsequent studies inquired into whether psychological
  empowerment functioned as a mediator for workplace performance, or
  incorporated the concept or measurement thereof into studies
  investigating the antecedents to turnover intentions. This line of
  research generally finds that psychological empowerment plays a
  positive mediating role in helping to increase Organizational
  Citizenship Behavior (OCB)<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn9">9</xref> and
  levels of performance
  (<xref alt="Taylor 2013" rid="ref-taylor2013" ref-type="bibr">Taylor
  2013</xref>), workplace satisfaction and organizational commitment
  (<xref alt="Liden, Wayne, and Sparrowe 2000" rid="ref-liden2000" ref-type="bibr">Liden,
  Wayne, and Sparrowe 2000</xref>), and mediates the effect of
  perception of authentic leadership from one’s supervisor
  (<xref alt="Shapira-Lishchinsky and Tsemach 2014" rid="ref-shapira-lishchinsky2014" ref-type="bibr">Shapira-Lishchinsky
  and Tsemach 2014</xref>). However, the latter two of the cited studies
  (<xref alt="Liden, Wayne, and Sparrowe 2000" rid="ref-liden2000" ref-type="bibr">Liden,
  Wayne, and Sparrowe 2000</xref>;
  <xref alt="Shapira-Lishchinsky and Tsemach 2014" rid="ref-shapira-lishchinsky2014" ref-type="bibr">Shapira-Lishchinsky
  and Tsemach 2014</xref>), which explore psychological empowerment as
  mediator for other outcomes, are questionable and should be reviewed
  with increased scrutiny before the reported findings are readily
  accepted<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn10">10</xref>.</p>
  <p>Research by Taylor
  (<xref alt="2013" rid="ref-taylor2013" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>) is
  the least problematic of these studies and is easily summarized. Goal
  setting plans by organizations positively influenced psychological
  empowerment and helpful and cooperative behavior toward other
  employees in the organization (i.e., ‘organizational citizenship
  behavior’ toward individuals). Goal setting increased self-reports of
  individual-oriented organizational performance behavior
  (OCBI)<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn11">11</xref> more so than
  self-reported organization-oriented performance behaviors
  (OCBO)<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn12">12</xref>. Perceived difficulty
  of goals<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn13">13</xref> positively influenced
  both OCBI and OCBO. Perception that job goals are clear, specific, and
  fully understood
  (goal-specificity)<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn14">14</xref> did not
  directly influence either OCBI or OCBO. However, goal-specificity
  indirectly influenced OCBI through the indirect effect of
  psychological empowerment. In other words, perception that job goals
  are clear, specific, and fully understood positively influences
  psychological empowerment which in turn indirectly influences
  individual-oriented performance (OCBI). Goal-specificity and
  goal-difficulty both positively influenced psychological empowerment,
  but the effect of goal-specificity was larger in comparison.</p>
  <sec id="recommended-intervention-strategies">
    <title>Recommended Intervention Strategies</title>
    <p>Review of the aforementioned studies conveys the impression that
    anything which may increase any of the four components of
    psychological empowerment should result in positive improvement in
    worker performance, enthusiasm on the job, and helpful workplace
    behaviors. This, however, tells us little more than what may be
    obvious without providing specific interventions on how to go about
    doing so. That is, the results of Taylor
    (<xref alt="2013" rid="ref-taylor2013" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>)
    are derived from comparison of attitudinal surveys but stops short
    of testing specific intervention strategies. Moreover, the sample
    was comprised of Australian public service workers, which may limit
    external validity–not to suggest anything special about Australia
    but rather the potential differences between public service workers
    and others generally. Further research may help to confirm whether
    interventions providing specific and challenging goals promotes
    improved worker performance, organizational commitment, or other
    such Organizational Citizenship Behaviors.</p>
    <p>Perceiving the boss to be authentic, or otherwise nice, good, and
    honest, increases the degree to which a worker feels like they have
    an impact at work, but the research showing this also shows that
    perceiving the boss to be authentic also increases one’s willingness
    to find work elsewhere
    (<xref alt="Shapira-Lishchinsky and Tsemach 2014" rid="ref-shapira-lishchinsky2014" ref-type="bibr">Shapira-Lishchinsky
    and Tsemach 2014</xref>). Said another way, perceiving the boss to
    be an authentic leader <xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn15">15</xref>
    <italic>increases</italic> a worker’s intent to leave their current
    job. The recommendation when it comes to leadership is to “…promote
    high standards of authentic leadership”
    (<xref alt="Shapira-Lishchinsky and Tsemach 2014, 701" rid="ref-shapira-lishchinsky2014" ref-type="bibr">Shapira-Lishchinsky
    and Tsemach 2014, 701</xref>), which is not a recommendation but has
    more to do with a worker’s perception of the boss’s personal
    characteristics. Deriving meaning and feeling competent in one’s
    work significantly influences work satisfaction, organizational
    commitment, and better ratings of job performance from one’s
    supervisor
    (<xref alt="Liden, Wayne, and Sparrowe 2000" rid="ref-liden2000" ref-type="bibr">Liden,
    Wayne, and Sparrowe 2000</xref>), but this research is highly
    dubious since it shows findings that are contradictory: deriving
    meaning from one’s work increases work satisfaction but feeling
    competent in one’s work also <italic>decreases</italic> work
    satisfaction. These perplexing findings are likely the result of
    limitations or flaws of the research. Attempts to replicate findings
    in the future may help our understanding in this area.</p>
    <p>The best intervention suggestion comes from Taylor
    (<xref alt="2013" rid="ref-taylor2013" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>),</p>
    <disp-quote>
      <p>“The findings suggest that public managers can promote OCB from
      goal-setting plans in two ways. One is to ensure that the
      goal-setting plans are well designed and implemented. In
      particular, challenging goals that are accepted by employees can
      motivate higher levels of performance. Another is to improve
      employees’ views of their work environment and their individual
      capacity so that they feel psychologically empowered at work. To
      encourage employees to see their job as more meaningful and to
      satisfy their self-efficacy and self-determination needs, managers
      should help employees understand the scope of their job and
      responsibilities, articulate the overlap between the agency’s
      goals and the employees’ personal goals, and demonstrate support
      for employees in their pursuit of the goals (e.g., provide access
      to appropriate professional development programs)”
      (<xref alt="2013, 461" rid="ref-taylor2013" ref-type="bibr">2013,
      461</xref>).</p>
    </disp-quote>
    <p>Thus, organizations that set specific and difficult job goals may
    increase workers psychological empowerment and helpful performance
    behavior towards individuals in the organization. In particular,
    setting job goals may positively influence psychological empowerment
    which in turn is expected to improve levels of performance directed
    to help co-workers and benefit the broader organization.
    Psychological empowerment increases for employees who feel their job
    goals require a high degree of competence and are demanding. The
    same goes for employees who feel that their work goals are clear,
    specific, and fully understood.</p>
  </sec>
</sec>
<sec id="turnover-intention">
  <title>Turnover Intention</title>
  <p>A related line of research in management and organizational studies
  inquired into factors related to voluntary turnover, which include
  empowerment among others such as job satisfaction and organizational
  commitment. However, these studies do not maintain a strict focus on
  the presence and effect of psychological empowerment, and the 12-item
  scale is not used to measure empowerment in the following studies. At
  least one study measures empowerment by use of a single item measure
  on a 5-point agree/disagree Likert response option format, “Employees
  have a feeling of personal empowerment with respect to work
  processes.”
  (<xref alt="Pitts, Marvel, and Fernandez 2011" rid="ref-pitts2011" ref-type="bibr">Pitts,
  Marvel, and Fernandez 2011</xref>). Other research includes
  measurement of constructs which tangentially relate to the conceptual
  components of psychological empowerment without referencing them as
  such. For instance, as part of the measure for “functional
  preferences” Bertelli
  (<xref alt="2007" rid="ref-bertelli2007" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>)
  measures “intrinsic motivation” with three survey items drawn from the
  Federal Human Capital Survey (FHCS): “Employees have a feeling of
  empowerment and ownership of work processes.”, “My work gives me a
  feeling of personal accomplishment.”, “I like the kind of work I do.”
  The other half of the comprised “functional preferences” measure
  includes items intent on measuring <italic>job involvement</italic>:
  “My talents are used well in the workplace.”, “I recommend my
  organization as a good place to work.”, “The work I do is
  important.”</p>
  <p>The variable use of different measurement items speaks to the
  discrepancies noted in results across multiple studies by Tett and
  Meyer
  (<xref alt="1993" rid="ref-tett1993" ref-type="bibr">1993</xref>). In
  their meta-analysis, they attempt to untangle the variable findings
  from the disparate use of multiple measures of similar or identical
  constructs. Their aim was to compare job satisfaction and
  organizational commitment “as unique precursors of employee
  withdrawal…”</p>
  <disp-quote>
    <p>“Overall, results support the view that satisfaction and
    commitment each contribute uniquely to the turnover process. Those
    contributions, however, are largely limited to intention/cognitions,
    and depend on the choice of measures.”
    (<xref alt="Tett and Meyer 1993, 279" rid="ref-tett1993" ref-type="bibr">Tett
    and Meyer 1993, 279</xref>).</p>
  </disp-quote>
  <p>The authors say that job satisfaction and [self-reported] turnover
  intention is sometimes included into an index of “withdrawal
  cognitions”, which refers simply to thoughts of quitting and intention
  to search for alternative employment. However, turnover intention is
  conceived as a conscious and deliberate willfulness to leave the
  organization. That is, turnover intention is conceptually different
  from a set of “withdrawal cognitions”. In other words, definitive
  intention to leave the job is different in that it is serious and
  intentional rather than merely passive thoughts about quitting.</p>
  <p>The first set of hypotheses (Hypothesis 1a and 1b) expect that
  organizational commitment should show stronger negative correlation
  than job satisfaction with turnover intention (H<sub>1a</sub>) and
  actual turnover (H<sub>1b</sub>). The authors found that job
  satisfaction showed a stronger negative relationship with turnover
  intention than when compared with organizational commitment. This
  would imply, simply, that higher job satisfaction is negatively
  correlated with turnover intention. However, once the more deliberate
  and serious turnover intention is detached from the aforementioned set
  of passive “withdrawal cognitions”, the strength of the negative
  relationship is lessened substantially. Ultimately, the findings
  suggest that organizational commitment and job satisfaction are
  relatively equal in importance for predicting either serious turnover
  intention or withdrawal cognitions
  (<xref alt="Tett and Meyer 1993, 280" rid="ref-tett1993" ref-type="bibr">Tett
  and Meyer 1993, 280</xref>).</p>
  <p>What is important to note, however, is that organizational
  commitment showed a much stronger negative relationship with actual
  turnover (contra. Passive thoughts or deliberate intention). The point
  is not only that organization commitment is likely more important than
  job satisfaction at predicting actual turnover, but crucially that an
  “intention to leave” measure is not viable as a proxy for actual
  turnover despite its predictive power
  (<xref alt="Tett and Meyer 1993" rid="ref-tett1993" ref-type="bibr">Tett
  and Meyer 1993</xref>). Perhaps just as important, the authors also
  note concerns with available measures for job satisfaction. They
  question the content of job satisfaction measures used in prior
  studies owing to “…contamination by items pertaining to withdrawal
  cognitions” and present a list of studies where such contamination was
  evident
  (<xref alt="Tett and Meyer 1993, 283" rid="ref-tett1993" ref-type="bibr">Tett
  and Meyer 1993, 283</xref>). In other words, items measuring job
  satisfaction commonly include items that also measured thoughts about
  quitting.</p>
  <p>The ultimate takeaway appreciable here is that researchers
  interested in ascertaining whether job satisfaction or organizational
  commitment are related to turnover are probably better off
  constructing and validating measurement scales <italic>ex
  novo</italic> (i.e., from the beginning).</p>
  <p>Beyond the accounting of the study by Tett and Meyer
  (<xref alt="1993" rid="ref-tett1993" ref-type="bibr">1993</xref>),
  this review finds that scholars from different fields approach
  questions related to empowerment in the workplace, job satisfaction,
  turnover and intention, and organizational commitment in distinct ways
  that place stronger emphasis on some factors over others. Of course,
  this is obvious–a trained economist is apt to approach questions about
  turnover intent by way of reviewing and comparing an organization’s
  incentive structure. This seems to be the case for the study conducted
  by Bertelli
  (<xref alt="2007" rid="ref-bertelli2007" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>),
  who compared the effect of the aforementioned “functional preferences”
  as a determinant for turnover intention between two distinct
  samples–one where performance-based pay reforms were put in-place for
  supervisors but not for non-supervisors, compared to another where no
  such merit-based pay reforms were enacted.</p>
  <p>To summarize, Bertelli
  (<xref alt="2007" rid="ref-bertelli2007" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>)
  finds that it is easier to retain supervisors in federal agencies (the
  Internal Revenue Service, IRS, and Office of the Comptroller of the
  Currency, OCC) who feel like their work is important, who like their
  work and gain feelings of accomplishment from it (i.e., “functional
  preferences”). This applies to employees who are Non-supervisors too,
  but non-supervisors are also more likely to stay when they view their
  workplace as friendly. A friendly work environment is not related to
  turnover intention for supervisors. Perceptions of inadequate
  pay<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn16">16</xref> impacts the likelihood of
  turnover intention for non-supervisors. To put simply, federal agency
  jobs like the IRS and OCC for people in non-supervisory positions that
  are not perceived as financially and psychologically rewarding are
  more likely to see increased turnover from non-supervisors. Having
  friendly coworkers helps, as does feeling like the work is important
  and feelings of accomplishment, but perceptions of inadequate pay,
  micromanaging boss, and merit-based performance incentives hanging
  over head all work to increase likelihood for turnover among
  non-supervisors. Those in supervisor positions are best retained when
  they find their work important and personally rewarding–perceptions of
  inadequate pay doesn’t drive turnover intention for supervisors.</p>
  <p>A brief note on the method. Bertelli writes
  (<xref alt="2007" rid="ref-bertelli2007" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>),</p>
  <disp-quote>
    <p>“The OCC is included in this study as a”control” group for
    examining the effect of perceptions of the management incentives
    unique to the IRS. OCC, located with the IRS in the U.S. Department
    of the Treasury, is the regulator of U.S. banks, and its employees
    engage in similar accounting oversight (i.e., auditing) as that
    performed by the IRS at the bank rather than at the individual and
    corporate levels. Both subagencies have a nationwide staff, and
    their employees possess generally similar backgrounds in accounting
    and financial matters. If there are unobserved attributes correlated
    with the responses to questions regarding performance incentives
    specific to the IRS, they can reasonably be addressed by the
    comparison between results for IRS and OCC supervisors. Among those
    attributes is the pay-banding system. In the absence of questions
    related specifically to pay-banding to facilitate a direct test,
    comparison of these groups is suggestive evidence of the effect of
    pay-banding on bureaucrats’ intent to leave their jobs. When
    combined with the information included in survey responses, this
    comparison provides significant leverage in understanding the
    effects of performance incentives on turnover intention.”
    (<xref alt="2007, 239–40" rid="ref-bertelli2007" ref-type="bibr">2007,
    239–40</xref>)</p>
  </disp-quote>
  <p>The results of a Probit regression analysis for determinants of
  turnover intention for supervisors across the two samples shows that
  only “functional preferences” and being employed by the IRS negatively
  predict turnover intention. Bertelli’s study takes the difference of
  agency employment as a proxy for the effect of the pay-banding reform
  scheme–that is, “In the absence of questions related specifically to
  pay-banding to facilitate a direct test, comparison of these groups is
  suggestive evidence of the effect of pay-banding on bureaucrats’
  intent to leave their jobs.”
  (<xref alt="Bertelli 2007, 240" rid="ref-bertelli2007" ref-type="bibr">Bertelli
  2007, 240</xref>).</p>
  <p>An alternative interpretation may omit any acknowledgement of the
  pay-banding scheme enacted for supervisors in the IRS, stating simply
  be that working for the OCC as a supervisor positively predicts
  turnover intention among supervisors. The author relies on the strong
  assumption that the two samples match closely enough that differences
  attributed to agency employment serve to indicate the effect of the
  performance-based pay reforms. However, by this logic, any differences
  between the two agencies in organizational or employee policies
  pertaining to supervisors can account for the differential effect. It
  isn’t simply that the model doesn’t account for every possible
  difference between the two agencies, but rather that the dummy effect
  of being employed as a supervisor in one agency rather another is
  posited to indicate the effect of this specific pay-banding scheme
  enacted within the IRS.</p>
  <p>Additionally, Bertelli
  (<xref alt="2007" rid="ref-bertelli2007" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>)
  notes the striking insignificance of negative perceptions of pay
  quality for supervisors in both the IRS and OCC samples. A single-item
  question measures this attitude about quality of pay, “How do you rate
  the amount of pay you get on your job?” where response options range
  across a 5-point scale from very poor to very good. From what can be
  gathered, it appears that higher ratings about quality of pay were not
  significant predictors of turnover intention. The mean response for
  quality of pay across the whole sample (<inline-formula><alternatives>
  <tex-math><![CDATA[n = 1842]]></tex-math>
  <mml:math display="inline" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1842</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>)
  was <inline-formula><alternatives>
  <tex-math><![CDATA[3.635]]></tex-math>
  <mml:math display="inline" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mn>3.635</mml:mn></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>
  with a standard deviation of <inline-formula><alternatives>
  <tex-math><![CDATA[1.003]]></tex-math>
  <mml:math display="inline" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mn>1.003</mml:mn></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>.
  The mean response for supervisors only was not displayed in the
  study.</p>
  <p>As an aside, Bertelli measures quality of pay with a single-item,
  but does not take into consideration any other forms of compensation,
  especially those unique benefits related to federal employment
  compared to similar jobs in the private sector. Anecdotally, private
  contractors recruit large amount of veteran service members for their
  specific service-related skill sets by offering appealing payment
  incentives; but working as a private contractor does not always come
  with the benefits or other compensatory incentives afforded by work as
  an employee, nor as an employee of the federal government. The
  decision between working in the public or private sector for the same
  kind of work may come down to such a comparative assessment of the
  financial security offered by federal government employment over
  self-employed contractor work. Although the compensation across the
  two agencies is likely to be similar, if not identical, the notion
  that quality of pay or compensation/benefits is insignificant to
  turnover intention, or actual turnover for that matter, is
  questionable. Especially considering that pay quality across both
  agencies was a significant predictor of turnover intention for
  non-supervisors. Bertelli doesn’t include descriptions of the average
  reported income for the studied samples, nor a reference to the
  relative pay scales for government employees that would apply to
  either agency, nor is any consideration made with regard to the
  overarching compensation/benefits structure. The quality of pay is
  demonstrably insignificant for turnover intention, but this should not
  be striking nor surprising for those who have reached supervisor
  status while employed with the federal government; they are paid quite
  well overall.</p>
  <p>In contrast, Pitts, Marvel, and Fernandez
  (<xref alt="2011" rid="ref-pitts2011" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>)
  does take <italic>benefits satisfaction</italic> into account when
  inquiring why federal employees choose to leave either their
  respective agencies or government work
  outright<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn17">17</xref>. However, these
  authors also minimize the impact of pay on turnover intention but rely
  on self-reports of pay
  satisfaction<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn18">18</xref> while also asking
  confounding satisfaction questions related to benefits (e.g., health
  insurance, retirement benefits, life
  insurance)<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn19">19</xref>, opportunities for
  advancement<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn20">20</xref>, and even job
  satisfaction<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn21">21</xref>. All these are
  arguably related to the same underlying factor of compensation someone
  takes into consideration when searching for a job. And this notional
  latent factor is likely crucial to understand the reasons for both
  recruitment <italic>and</italic> retention. The reasons why a person
  intends to leave may not be related to their financial situation if
  said situation is far more comfortable in government work than
  elsewhere. Yet the reason for choosing to get into government work in
  the first place is likely strongly related to the perceived
  prospective financial security of working in the federal government,
  and might be a foundational reason for the prevalence of inter-agency
  turnover compared to government turnover in general. About
  <inline-formula><alternatives>
  <tex-math><![CDATA[16.1\%]]></tex-math>
  <mml:math display="inline" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>16.1</mml:mn><mml:mi>%</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>
  of federal employees in the sample stated their intent to leave their
  agency for another agency within the federal government. In
  comparison, about <inline-formula><alternatives>
  <tex-math><![CDATA[3.6\%]]></tex-math>
  <mml:math display="inline" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3.6</mml:mn><mml:mi>%</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>
  of federal employees plan to leave government work all
  together<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn22">22</xref>.</p>
  <sec id="recommended-interventions-to-reduce-turnover-and-turnover-intention">
    <title>Recommended Interventions to Reduce Turnover and Turnover
    Intention</title>
    <p>The literature reviewed here is mostly concerned with turnover
    intention for government employees. To summarize the findings and
    recommended interventions of Pitts, Marvel, and Fernandez
    (<xref alt="2011" rid="ref-pitts2011" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>),
    workplace satisfaction plays largest role in predicting intention to
    leave an agency among government employees. Advancement
    opportunities and age also plays a significant role for agency
    turnover intention. The most important factors predicting whether an
    employee intends to leave federal government are age, whether an
    employee is non-White, and job satisfaction.</p>
    <p>These authors suggested a couple of interventions to decrease
    turnover for government agencies. First, offer advancement
    opportunities along with professional development programs in hopes
    that it will motivate new and younger employees to say at their
    agency instead of move between government agencies. Second, relax
    performance-based workplace culture (merit-based pay/advancement,
    incentives) for new and younger employees as such performance-based
    cultural work environment predicts intra-agency turnover intention
    among this group
    (<xref alt="Pitts, Marvel, and Fernandez 2011" rid="ref-pitts2011" ref-type="bibr">Pitts,
    Marvel, and Fernandez 2011</xref>).</p>
    <p>As stated previously, Bertelli
    (<xref alt="2007" rid="ref-bertelli2007" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>)
    finds that “functional preferences” (i.e., a latent factor indicated
    by two component measurements of job involvement and intrinsic
    motivation) and solidarity preferences (e.g., “This is a friendly
    place to work.”) decrease the likelihood that agency bureaucrats
    will leave their government jobs
    (<xref alt="2007, 253" rid="ref-bertelli2007" ref-type="bibr">2007,
    253</xref>). Bertelli does not recommend interventions outright,
    there may be distinct strategies implied depending on whether the
    target workers in question are supervisors or non-supervisors.
    However, since the perception of a friendly work environment reduces
    the likelihood of turnover intention among non-supervisor employees,
    it is unclear how or what interventions could be enacted to make the
    workplace appear friendly, generally speaking. Although
    performance-based incentives are weakly significant in predicting
    whether supervisors retain their jobs, such incentives imposed upon
    non-supervisor employees may increase turnover intention. However,
    bear in mind that turnover intention may not reflect actual turnover
    rates
    (<xref alt="Tett and Meyer 1993" rid="ref-tett1993" ref-type="bibr">Tett
    and Meyer 1993</xref>).</p>
  </sec>
</sec>
<sec id="discussion-and-conclusion">
  <title>Discussion and Conclusion</title>
  <p>Based on the review of the cited literature related to turnover
  intention for government employees, the findings suggest that
  government employees are generally more likely to stay for obvious
  reasons such as financial security and retirement potential. It seems
  more apparent that simply getting a federal government job matters
  more than which agency one settles with, and the longer one stays
  working in government then the less likely they are to leave. For
  instance, one finding suggests that a workplace environment with a
  “performance culture” (i.e., a work environment that incorporates
  merit-based pay and advancement incentives) <italic>increases</italic>
  turnover intention but only inter-agency turnover, i.e., those who
  plan to leave their agency to take another job within the federal
  government. Absent here is consideration as to whether government work
  in general is perceived to be more attractive compared to work outside
  of the federal government for most current government employees. If it
  is, then the reasons for wanting to leave are unlikely to be entirely
  related to income and benefits. That is to say, there is likely a
  substantive difference between those who work for federal government
  agencies and those who don’t.</p>
  <p>This references back to the earlier literature on psychological
  empowerment, which emphasizes a focus on the individual differences
  between workers in terms of the meaning, impact, competence, and
  autonomy they derive from the work they do. This literature draws from
  organizational psychologically and recommends interventions related to
  re-framing the workers interpretation of workplace outcomes and
  proposes the increased use of self-empowerment programs
  (<xref alt="Thomas and Velthouse 1990" rid="ref-thomas1990" ref-type="bibr">Thomas
  and Velthouse 1990</xref>), and generally recommends setting goals
  that are both challenging and well understood (i.e., specific)
  (<xref alt="Taylor 2013" rid="ref-taylor2013" ref-type="bibr">Taylor
  2013</xref>). Although the empowerment literature makes it clear that
  work satisfaction and positive perceptions of workplace leadership
  either increase or are increased by psychological empowerment, there
  is no clear way to intervene and adjust the perceptions of the
  individual worker. In that respect, it appears that the early
  recommendations by Ashforth
  (<xref alt="1989" rid="ref-ashforth1989" ref-type="bibr">1989</xref>)
  may be the most practical and sensible overall, “…provide realistic
  job previews, specific and challenging goals, prompt and balanced
  feedback, contingent reinforcement, and appropriate role models…”, and
  remove obstacles which impede personal control
  (<xref alt="1989, 234" rid="ref-ashforth1989" ref-type="bibr">1989,
  234</xref>). In addition, delegating more influence to lower level
  employees in ways that make their input significant to workplace
  strategies and decision-making may also increase some demonstrably
  important component factors of empowerment such as competence, impact,
  and self-determination (i.e., autonomy).</p>
  <p>In contrast, the turnover literature reviewed here focuses
  primarily on the organizational structure and workplace environment
  intervention. Although workers who feel like their work is important
  and gain feelings of accomplishment from it are far easier to retain,
  these attitudes become more significant to those who are in supervisor
  roles–i.e., those who are arguably already well settled into a job or
  career. The workplace environment and its overarching structural
  arrangement is most important to reduce turnover among the young and
  the restless
  (<xref alt="Bertelli 2007" rid="ref-bertelli2007" ref-type="bibr">Bertelli
  2007</xref>). Quality of pay, benefits, opportunities for advancement,
  and overall financial security are organizational factors that are
  significant to consider if the goal is to reduce turnover intention
  (<xref alt="Pitts, Marvel, and Fernandez 2011" rid="ref-pitts2011" ref-type="bibr">Pitts,
  Marvel, and Fernandez 2011</xref>), and possibly actual turnover rates
  as well. Although recruiters and hiring managers might love to hear a
  potential hire genuinely respond to the question “Why do you want to
  work here?” with “To increase my sense of psychological empowerment”,
  the real motivation for many potential and current employees may still
  be those basic instrumental factors.</p>
  <p>A major aspect underlying the literature reviewed here is
  organizational contextual factors versus individual differences.
  Thomas and Velthouse
  (<xref alt="1990" rid="ref-thomas1990" ref-type="bibr">1990</xref>)
  contended that empowerment refers to the motivational content of a
  nontraditional form of management (a new paradigm of motivation, as
  they say) in which management establishes controls to foster an
  emphasis or internalized commitment to the task
  <italic>itself</italic>. Workers are “pulled” toward doing the tasks
  rather than “pushed” towards it because the tasks are made to be
  meaningful; workers identify with the task; and there is expressive
  value in doing the task. To put another way, figuring out ways to have
  workers want to do the tasks rather than simply making them do the
  tasks. Authors of the empowerment literature say that prior research
  professes the idea that external variables such as organizational
  structure, managerial strategies, and types of information all work as
  interventions to produce increased feelings of empowerment (i.e.,
  self-efficacy) in work. In other words, the structural context of the
  organized work environment induces greater empowerment within the
  worker, and thus enhances their motivation to initiate, persist, and
  better perform. The empowerment authors view this as lacking as it
  doesn’t take into account how the perspective of the subject (i.e.,
  subjective) influences the cognitive variables thought to determine
  feelings of empowerment. Stated otherwise, prior research doesn’t take
  into account the influence of individual differences
  (<xref alt="Thomas and Velthouse 1990" rid="ref-thomas1990" ref-type="bibr">Thomas
  and Velthouse 1990</xref>).</p>
  <p>Yet it appears as though that when organizational factors are
  relatively stable and insignificant–mainly for those workers who are
  in comfortable and secure supervisory positions–then turnover intent
  and actual turnover rates among them are likely to be more strongly
  associated with individual differences such as the components of
  psychological empowerment. Those who are relatively more secure and in
  roles in which they not only feel, but actually are in fact, impactful
  and competent, are seemingly more likely to appraise their work
  conditions in terms of how satisfying it is to them, how meaningful it
  is, and how intrinsically motivated they are to continue doing such
  work. In essence, when certain needs are sufficiently met, then other
  factors take on more significance. This may explain why federal
  employees are more inclined to change agencies but do not quit
  government work outright
  (<xref alt="Bertelli 2007" rid="ref-bertelli2007" ref-type="bibr">Bertelli
  2007</xref>). In contrast, psychological empowerment and other such
  factors are muted <italic>unless</italic> the individual worker is in
  fact legitimately <italic>intrinsically motivated</italic> to do that
  work for the sake of doing the work <italic>itself</italic>.
  Otherwise, it should be presumed that most workers retain jobs
  motivated by external factors related to basic instrumental
  incentives. It may be the case that workers seek out particular jobs
  or types of work based on more <italic>internalized and
  integrated</italic> extrinsic motivations, which are the closest
  approximations to intrinsic motivation along the extrinsic to
  intrinsic motivational spectrum
  (<xref alt="Ryan and Deci 2000" rid="ref-ryan2000" ref-type="bibr">Ryan
  and Deci 2000</xref>,
  <xref alt="2017" rid="ref-ryan2017" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). That
  is to say, the initial choice of what work one wishes to get into is
  likely more powerful than palliative interventions such as
  self-empowerment programs.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="appendix-a">
  <title>Appendix A</title>
  <sec id="the-public-service-motivation-construct-and-scale">
    <title>The Public Service Motivation Construct and Scale</title>
    <p>The following is a brief overview of the Public Service
    Motivation scale and construct as developed by Perry
    (<xref alt="1996" rid="ref-perry1996" ref-type="bibr">1996</xref>).
    Perry defines Public Service Motivation (PSM), “as an individual’s
    predisposition to respond to motives grounded primarily or uniquely
    in public institutions”
    (<xref alt="1996, 6" rid="ref-perry1996" ref-type="bibr">1996,
    6</xref>). An interesting aspect of the PSM construct and scale is
    that it is predicated on a particular understanding of motivation
    rooted in evolutionary psychology, and is also found elsewhere in
    social psychology literature (For review, see
    <xref alt="Higgins and Nakkawita 2021, 88" rid="ref-higgins2021" ref-type="bibr">Higgins
    and Nakkawita 2021, 88</xref>). Here and in other related work,
    motives are driven by needs. In particular, certain “drive theories”
    of motivation suggest that humans recognize something as a ‘need’
    when its deprivation threatens our survival, our growth, or our
    ultimate life satisfaction and well-being. The motivation to fulfill
    unmet ‘needs’ may guide our behavior, impact on our thoughts,
    explain our selective attention and memory
    (<xref alt="Gardner, Pickett, and Brewer 2000" rid="ref-gardner2000" ref-type="bibr">Gardner,
    Pickett, and Brewer 2000</xref>;
    <xref alt="Hull 1943" rid="ref-hull1943" ref-type="bibr">Hull
    1943</xref>;
    <xref alt="Mcleod 2022" rid="ref-mcleod2022" ref-type="bibr">Mcleod
    2022</xref>). As it relates to PSM, Perry
    (<xref alt="1996" rid="ref-perry1996" ref-type="bibr">1996</xref>)
    recognized three analytically distinct motivational categories:
    rational, norm-based, and affective.</p>
    <disp-quote>
      <p>“Rational motives involve actions grounded in individual
      utility maximization. Norm-based motives refer to actions
      generated by efforts to conform to norms. Affective motives refer
      to those triggers of behavior that are grounded in emotional
      responses to various social contexts.”
      (<xref alt="Perry 1996, 6" rid="ref-perry1996" ref-type="bibr">Perry
      1996, 6</xref>)</p>
    </disp-quote>
    <p>The PSM scale development was based on conceptual dimensions
    which were categorized into the motivational categories. The final
    PSM scale was confirmed as having four component dimensions:
    attraction to public policy making, commitment to the public
    interest, compassion, and self-sacrifice. However, the initial
    analysis of the finalized PSM scale demonstrated no distinct
    difference in model fit between a three and four dimensional PSM
    model. The public interest and self-sacrifice component dimensions
    were highly correlated, and so a comparison between the three and
    four-dimensional model was done. The four dimensional model showed a
    slighter higher <inline-formula><alternatives>
    <tex-math><![CDATA[𝛘^2]]></tex-math>
    <mml:math display="inline" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:msup><mml:mi>𝛘</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>
    statistic, thus Perry
    (<xref alt="1996" rid="ref-perry1996" ref-type="bibr">1996</xref>)
    opted to retain the self-sacrifice dimension to maintain the four
    dimensional model of the PSM scale because, “it has had a historical
    connection to how we think about public service that is explicitly
    preserved by retaining the dimension.”
    (<xref alt="Perry 1996, 20" rid="ref-perry1996" ref-type="bibr">Perry
    1996, 20</xref>). However, it is recommended by Perry that further
    refinements to the PSM construct and scale be undertaken by future
    research.</p>
    <p>The four component dimensions of the Public Service Motivation
    scale are described below;</p>
    <def-list>
      <def-item>
        <term>Attraction to public policy making (rational
        motive)</term>
        <def>
          <p>Refers to a rational motive in which the opportunity to
          participation in the formation of public policy draws
          individuals to public service</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
      <def-item>
        <term>Commitment to the public interest (norm-based)</term>
        <def>
          <p>An altruistic desire to serve the public interest</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
      <def-item>
        <term>Compassion (aka “patriotism of benevolence”,
        affective)</term>
        <def>
          <p>An affective state that combines the love of regime values
          and the love of others which drives people to exemplify “a
          patriotism of benevolence”[^22]</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
      <def-item>
        <term>Self-sacrifice (unclear motive)</term>
        <def>
          <p>Refers to the willingness to substitute service to others
          for tangible personal rewards. In other words, the willingness
          of public servants to forego financial rewards for the
          intangible rewards received from serving the public.</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
    </def-list>
    <p>After refinements were made to the initial scale, the resulting
    Public Service Motivation Scale was finalized to include 24-items
    measuring four component dimensions. The PSM measurement items are
    measured with Likert type response options. The items are listed in
    the table below</p>
    <table-wrap>
      <caption>
        <p>Public Service Motivation Scale Item Wording
        (<xref alt="Perry 1996" rid="ref-perry1996" ref-type="bibr">Perry
        1996</xref>)</p>
      </caption>
      <table>
        <colgroup>
          <col width="10%" />
          <col width="24%" />
          <col width="65%" />
        </colgroup>
        <thead>
          <tr>
            <th>Motive type</th>
            <th>Component Dimension</th>
            <th>Item Wording</th>
          </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td>Rational Motive</td>
            <td>Public Policy Making</td>
            <td><list list-type="bullet">
              <list-item>
                <p>PSM 11 Politics is a dirty word. (Reversed)</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>PSM 27 The give and take of public policy making
                doesn’t appeal to me. (Reversed)</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>PSM 31 I don’t care much for politicians.
                (Reversed)</p>
              </list-item>
            </list></td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Norm-based motive</td>
            <td>Public Interest</td>
            <td><list list-type="bullet">
              <list-item>
                <p>PSM 16 It is hard for me to get intensely interested
                in what is going on in my community. (Reversed)</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>PSM 23 I unselfishly contribute to my community.</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>PSM 30 Meaningful public service is very important to
                me.</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>PSM 34 I would prefer seeing public officials do what
                is best for the whole community even if it harmed my
                interests.</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>PSM 39 I consider public service my civic duty.</p>
              </list-item>
            </list></td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Affective motive</td>
            <td>Compassion (aka “patriotism of benevolence”)</td>
            <td><list list-type="bullet">
              <list-item>
                <p>PSM 2 I am rarely moved by the plight of the
                underprivileged. (Reversed)</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>PSM 3 Most social programs are too vital to do
                without.</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>PSM 4 It is difficult for me to contain my feelings
                when I see people in distress.</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>PSM 8 To me, patriotism includes seeing to the
                welfare of others.</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>PSM 10 I seldom think about the welfare of people
                whom I don’t know personally. (Reversed)</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>PSM 13 I am often reminded by daily events about how
                dependent we are on one another.</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>PSM 24 I have little compassion for people in need
                who are unwilling to take the first step to help
                themselves. (Reversed)</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>PSM 40 There are few public programs that I
                wholeheartedly support. (Reversed)</p>
              </list-item>
            </list></td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Unclear</td>
            <td>Self-sacrifice</td>
            <td><list list-type="bullet">
              <list-item>
                <p>PSM 1 Making a difference in society means more to me
                than personal achievements.</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>PSM 5 I believe in putting duty before self.</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>PSM 6 Doing well financially is definitely more
                important to me than doing good deeds. (Reversed)</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>PSM 9 Much of what I do is for a cause bigger than
                myself.</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>PSM 12 Serving citizens would give me a good feeling
                even if no one paid me for it.</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>PSM 17 I feel people should give back to society more
                than they get from it.</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>PSM 19 I am one of those rare people who would risk
                personal loss to help someone else.</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>PSM 26 I am prepared to make enormous sacrifices for
                the good of society.</p>
              </list-item>
            </list></td>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
    </table-wrap>
  </sec>
</sec>
<sec id="appendix-b">
  <title>Appendix B</title>
  <sec id="methodological-notes-and-critiques-related-to-literature-on-psychological-empowerment">
    <title>Methodological Notes and Critiques Related to Literature on
    Psychological Empowerment</title>
    <sec id="on-the-measurement-of-psychological-empowerment-reivew-speicifc-to-spreitzer1995">
      <title>On the Measurement of Psychological Empowerment: Reivew
      Speicifc to Spreitzer
      (<xref alt="1995" rid="ref-spreitzer1995" ref-type="bibr">1995</xref>)</title>
      <p>As stated in the main text, the Psychological Empowerment scale
      measurement instrument includes 12-items with the component
      dimensions measured with three items each. In this case,
      psychological empowerment is understood as a common second-order
      latent factor that underlies the four latent component factors
      (e.g., meaning, impact, competence, self-determination). Initial
      analysis of the measurement scale revealed significant correlation
      between the component factors, suggesting a lack of discriminant
      validity between the four dimensional components of empowerment.
      Further research should be done to further refine the theory and
      measurement of psychological empowerment
      (<xref alt="Spreitzer 1995, 1458" rid="ref-spreitzer1995" ref-type="bibr">Spreitzer
      1995, 1458</xref>).</p>
      <p>Validity and reliability was assessed for the four components
      of empowerment by examination of the overall Cronbach’s alpha
      (<inline-formula><alternatives>
      <tex-math><![CDATA[\alpha]]></tex-math>
      <mml:math display="inline" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>)
      of the scale and the same was done for each component as well. The
      measurement scales for the four components of empowerment were
      found to be valid and moderately reliable. Second-order
      confirmatory factor analysis (CFA) was used to assess the
      convergent and discriminant validity of the empowerment measures
      in both samples. Second-order confirmatory factor analysis is
      structurally equivalent to first-order CFA: there is an
      unobservable latent factor (i.e., construct) theorized to be
      influential upon observable referents, or indicators. For
      second-order CFA, the latent factor is theorized to be a common
      higher level factor influential upon a set of other lower level
      latent component factors.</p>
      <p>It’s important to make a quick note on the survey sample and
      data collection strategy used in this study to develop and
      validate the measurement scale of psychological empowerment.
      Especially since this scale is referenced and drawn upon often in
      subsequent research. Survey data was collected for two distinct
      samples of a Fortune 50 industrial company. The first sample
      (<inline-formula><alternatives>
      <tex-math><![CDATA[n = 393]]></tex-math>
      <mml:math display="inline" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>393</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>)
      comprised of managers from across departments. Manager respondents
      were surveyed over a period of three years until a 100% response
      rate was achieved (this was not panel data). This first primary
      sample consisted of mid-level managers,
      <inline-formula><alternatives>
      <tex-math><![CDATA[93\%]]></tex-math>
      <mml:math display="inline" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>93</mml:mn><mml:mi>%</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>
      male, <inline-formula><alternatives>
      <tex-math><![CDATA[85\%]]></tex-math>
      <mml:math display="inline" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>85</mml:mn><mml:mi>%</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>
      White, average age of <inline-formula><alternatives>
      <tex-math><![CDATA[46]]></tex-math>
      <mml:math display="inline" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mn>46</mml:mn></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>
      years, an average tenure of <inline-formula><alternatives>
      <tex-math><![CDATA[13]]></tex-math>
      <mml:math display="inline" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mn>13</mml:mn></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>
      years at the company, and average time in position of
      <inline-formula><alternatives>
      <tex-math><![CDATA[3]]></tex-math>
      <mml:math display="inline" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>
      years. The extent that this sample is representative of people
      with jobs, generally speaking, is probably pretty low. But more
      importantly, the author was trying to develop and validate a novel
      measure of empowerment by testing it on a sample that is likely to
      be more empowered than the average worker. It is not clear why the
      sample was confined to this group, but it seems like it would have
      made more sense to randomly sample all employees.</p>
      <p>In contrast, the second sample was surveyed at two different
      intervals spanning five months in between survey administration,
      and consisted of (non-managerial) employees
      (<inline-formula><alternatives>
      <tex-math><![CDATA[n = 128]]></tex-math>
      <mml:math display="inline" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>128</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>)
      of the same company. The author reported a difference in
      measurement validity between the two samples; the Cronbach’s alpha
      for the overall measure of empowerment was
      <inline-formula><alternatives>
      <tex-math><![CDATA[\alpha = 0.72]]></tex-math>
      <mml:math display="inline" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.72</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>
      for the primary industrial sample of managers, but
      <inline-formula><alternatives>
      <tex-math><![CDATA[\alpha = 0.62]]></tex-math>
      <mml:math display="inline" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.62</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>
      for the second sample of employees. This calls into question
      whether the equivalence assumption
      (<xref alt="Pietryka and MacIntosh 2022" rid="ref-pietryka2022" ref-type="bibr">Pietryka
      and MacIntosh 2022</xref>) holds for this measurement scale.
      Additionally, the primary sample of managers were surveyed across
      a period of three years at the beginning of a managerial
      development program. Seeing as how these managers all work in the
      same company, it apparently wasn’t considered that any of the
      managers of the sample would talk to each other about the survey
      over the period of three years, which potentially may have
      contaminated the results of the study.</p>
      <p>Using the new measure for psychological empowerment, Spreitzer
      (<xref alt="1995" rid="ref-spreitzer1995" ref-type="bibr">1995</xref>)
      tested whether the scale significantly predicted two outcomes:
      managerial effectiveness and innovative behavior. The former was
      defined as, “the degree to which a manager fulfills or exceeds
      work role expectations”
      (<xref alt="1995, 1448" rid="ref-spreitzer1995" ref-type="bibr">1995,
      1448</xref>). Note that “managerial effectiveness” does not only
      pertain to workers who are employed as managers, but rather
      apparently refers to a kind of effectiveness which would be
      described as “managerial”. Spreitzer explains, “Because, by
      definition, empowered managers see themselves as competent and
      able to influence their jobs and work environments in meaningful
      ways, they are likely to proactively execute their job
      responsibilities by, for instance, anticipating problems and
      acting independently, and hence are likely to be seen as
      effective.”
      (<xref alt="1995, 1448" rid="ref-spreitzer1995" ref-type="bibr">1995,
      1448</xref>). Innovative behavior was defined as “the creation of
      something new or different”.</p>
      <p>It is unclear what survey items were used to measure these two
      behavioral outcomes, but both managerial effectiveness and
      innovative behavior was ascertained by questioning the subordinate
      employees of the managers from the primary sample. The two
      behavioral outcomes were found to be significantly related to
      empowerment, but the marginal fit of the model was said to be
      likely due to multicollinearity between those two behavioral
      outcomes.</p>
      <p>Spreitzer also fit a Multiple Indicators Multiple Causes
      (MIMIC) model to test whether certain factors were antecedent to
      empowerment. This attempt to identify individual and contextual
      factors antecedent to empowerment found partial support, but was
      not substantially convincing. Many of the independent constructs
      theorized to influence empowerment overlap in definition or
      description and are not independent in that they potentially cause
      or influence each other. Each factor is nevertheless theorized to
      have independent influence on empowerment. For example, feedback
      (i.e., information about performance) and self-esteem are
      considered as two independent factors that are antecedent to
      empowerment. The former contextual, the latter a dispositional
      trait. However, feedback on performance likely impacts self-esteem
      despite its conception as a stable and enduring disposition. That
      raises issues of endogeneity (two independent variables not so
      independent).</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="psychological-empowerment-as-a-mediator-review-specific-to-liden2000-and-shapira-lishchinsky2014">
      <title>Psychological Empowerment as a Mediator: Review Specific to
      Liden, Wayne, and Sparrowe
      (<xref alt="2000" rid="ref-liden2000" ref-type="bibr">2000</xref>)
      and Shapira-Lishchinsky and Tsemach
      (<xref alt="2014" rid="ref-shapira-lishchinsky2014" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>)</title>
      <p>As stated in the main text, two of the three studies examining
      psychological empowerment as a mediating variable appeared
      problematic upon review. What follows are my initial impressions
      and critiques upon review of Liden, Wayne, and Sparrowe
      (<xref alt="2000" rid="ref-liden2000" ref-type="bibr">2000</xref>)
      and Shapira-Lishchinsky and Tsemach
      (<xref alt="2014" rid="ref-shapira-lishchinsky2014" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>).</p>
      <p>The earliest of these studies shows that the meaning and
      competence dimensions of psychological empowerment have
      significant influence on organizational commitment
      (<xref alt="Liden, Wayne, and Sparrowe 2000" rid="ref-liden2000" ref-type="bibr">Liden,
      Wayne, and Sparrowe 2000</xref>). However, the cited study appears
      somewhat questionable in terms of method and measurement of the
      relevant variables. The cited study uses the term “mediator
      variables” to describe the empowerment component dimensions, but
      the analysis conducted appears to have consisted of multivariate
      OLS. The dependent variables were workplace satisfaction,
      organizational commitment, and job performance, whereas the
      independent variables included every component of empowerment,
      leadership-member exchange (relationship with leadership) and
      team-member exchange (relationship with coworkers), and job
      characteristics.</p>
      <p>The authors present three OLS models, with the last
      multivariate OLS model being the most significant as it includes
      both the “mediator variables” (empowerment components) and other
      independent variables all together. Looking at this Table 4
      (<xref alt="Liden, Wayne, and Sparrowe 2000, 413" rid="ref-liden2000" ref-type="bibr">Liden,
      Wayne, and Sparrowe 2000, 413</xref>), the only statistically
      significant positively related independent variables to work
      satisfaction are job characteristics and the meaning component of
      empowerment, whereas competence shows a significant negative
      influence on work satisfaction–on average and holding all else
      equal. This finding in Table 4 suggests that an increase in
      feelings of competence in one’s job decreases work satisfaction.
      In addition, The measurement for work satisfaction was measured by
      marking “yes” for adjectives connotating satisfaction, but
      responses are coded so that a “yes” = 3, whereas a “no” = 0. This
      coding scheme would seemingly inflate the Cronbach’s alpha for the
      measure of work satisfaction and doesn’t convey convincing
      construct nor face validity. The measurement of the relevant
      variables (save for the empowerment components) and the analysis
      of the study makes the reported findings in Liden, Wayne, and
      Sparrowe
      (<xref alt="2000" rid="ref-liden2000" ref-type="bibr">2000</xref>)
      article appear dubious.</p>
      <p>A relatively more recent study examined whether psychological
      empowerment serves as a mediating variable between teachers
      perceptions of authentic leadership and OCB and withdraw behaviors
      (e.g., lateness and voluntary absence frequency)
      (<xref alt="Shapira-Lishchinsky and Tsemach 2014" rid="ref-shapira-lishchinsky2014" ref-type="bibr">Shapira-Lishchinsky
      and Tsemach 2014</xref>). The essential findings of the research
      intuitively suggest that when the boss is perceived as an
      ‘authentic leader’, employees (teachers) are increasingly
      motivated to perform above and beyond what is required of them and
      report no intent to leave their current job. Here, issues arise in
      the description and measurement of psychological empowerment,
      which somewhat undermine the reported findings. The cited authors
      employ a selective approach to the use of different measurement
      scales, and when it came to psychological empowerment, chose to
      reduce the component dimensions down to two and selected eight of
      the original 12 survey items.</p>
      <p>The confirmatory factor analysis conducted by
      Shapira-Lishchinsky and Tsemach
      (<xref alt="2014" rid="ref-shapira-lishchinsky2014" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>)
      yielded two factors but the method is literally an analysis meant
      to confirm the number of expected factors previously theorized.
      The authors operationally conceived of psychological empowerment
      as a two dimensional construct. The authors limited the number of
      factors down to two, selected 8 out of 12 items from the original
      psychological empowerment scale, and then conducted an analysis to
      confirm that survey data sufficiently loads onto only two factors.
      The thing is, the original psychological empowerment scale is
      comprised of four latent factors derived from 12-items, where 3
      items are used to measure each component factor. The original
      conception of psychological empowerment has four (latent)
      dimensions. Seeing as how the analysis by Spreitzer
      (<xref alt="1995" rid="ref-spreitzer1995" ref-type="bibr">1995</xref>)
      found that divergent validity was lacking among the component
      factors, the selective use of various survey items from the
      original scale is likely to only exacerbate such issues of scale
      validity.</p>
    </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec id="references">
    <title>References</title>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="ref-ashforth1989">
        <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name><surname>Ashforth</surname><given-names>Blake E</given-names></name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The experience of powerlessness in organizations</article-title>
          <source>Organizational Behavior and Human Decision Processes</source>
          <year iso-8601-date="1989">1989</year>
          <volume>43</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <issn>0749-5978</issn>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0749-5978(89)90051-4</pub-id>
          <fpage>207</fpage>
          <lpage>242</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-bertelli2007">
        <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name><surname>Bertelli</surname><given-names>Anthony M.</given-names></name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Determinants of Bureaucratic Turnover Intention: Evidence from the Department of the Treasury</article-title>
          <source>Journal of Public Administration Research and Theory: J-PART</source>
          <publisher-name>[Oxford University Press, Journal of Public Administration Research and Theory, Inc., Public Management Research Association]</publisher-name>
          <year iso-8601-date="2007">2007</year>
          <date-in-citation content-type="access-date"><year iso-8601-date="2024-02-27">2024</year><month>02</month><day>27</day></date-in-citation>
          <volume>17</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <issn>1053-1858</issn>
          <uri>https://www.jstor.org/stable/4139743</uri>
          <fpage>235</fpage>
          <lpage>258</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-dahl1961">
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name><surname>Dahl</surname><given-names>Robert A.</given-names></name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Who Governs?: Democracy and Power in an American City</source>
          <publisher-name>Yale University Press</publisher-name>
          <year iso-8601-date="1961-01-01">1961</year><month>01</month><day>01</day>
          <isbn>978-0-300-10392-2</isbn>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-dahl2015">
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name><surname>Dahl</surname><given-names>Robert A.</given-names></name>
            <name><surname>Shapiro</surname><given-names>Ian</given-names></name>
          </person-group>
          <source>On democracy</source>
          <publisher-name>Yale University Press</publisher-name>
          <publisher-loc>New Haven</publisher-loc>
          <year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year>
          <edition>Second edition.</edition>
          <isbn>978-0-300-23332-2 0-300-23332-9</isbn>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.12987/9780300233322</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-deci2012">
        <element-citation publication-type="chapter">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name><surname>Deci</surname><given-names>Edward L.</given-names></name>
            <name><surname>Ryan</surname><given-names>Richard M.</given-names></name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Self-determination theory</article-title>
          <source>Handbook of theories of social psychology, Vol. 1</source>
          <publisher-name>Sage Publications Ltd</publisher-name>
          <publisher-loc>Thousand Oaks, CA</publisher-loc>
          <year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year>
          <isbn>978-0-85702-960-7</isbn>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4135/9781446249215.n21</pub-id>
          <fpage>416</fpage>
          <lpage>436</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-hackman1974">
        <element-citation publication-type="report">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name><surname>Hackman</surname><given-names>J. Richard</given-names></name>
            <name><surname>Oldham</surname><given-names>Greg R.</given-names></name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The Job Diagnostic Survey: An Instrument for the Diagnosis of Jobs and the Evaluation of Job Redesign Projects</article-title>
          <publisher-name>Yale University</publisher-name>
          <year iso-8601-date="1974-05">1974</year><month>05</month>
          <date-in-citation content-type="access-date"><year iso-8601-date="2024-03-28">2024</year><month>03</month><day>28</day></date-in-citation>
          <uri>https://eric.ed.gov/?id=ED099580</uri>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-hackman1975">
        <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name><surname>Hackman</surname><given-names>J. Richard</given-names></name>
            <name><surname>Oldham</surname><given-names>Greg R.</given-names></name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Development of the Job Diagnostic Survey</article-title>
          <source>Journal of Applied Psychology</source>
          <publisher-name>American Psychological Association</publisher-name>
          <publisher-loc>US</publisher-loc>
          <year iso-8601-date="1975">1975</year>
          <volume>60</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <issn>1939-1854</issn>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/h0076546</pub-id>
          <fpage>159</fpage>
          <lpage>170</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-higgins2021">
        <element-citation publication-type="chapter">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name><surname>Higgins</surname><given-names>E Tory</given-names></name>
            <name><surname>Nakkawita</surname><given-names>Emily</given-names></name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Motives Working Together: Value, Truth, and Control in Goal Selection and Pursuit</article-title>
          <source>Social psychology : Handbook of basic principles</source>
          <person-group person-group-type="editor">
            <name><surname>Lange</surname><given-names>Paul A. M. van</given-names></name>
            <name><surname>Kruglanski</surname><given-names>Arie W.</given-names></name>
            <name><surname>Higgins</surname><given-names>E Tory</given-names></name>
          </person-group>
          <publisher-name>The Guilford Press</publisher-name>
          <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
          <year iso-8601-date="2021">2021</year>
          <edition>Third edition.</edition>
          <isbn>978-1-4625-4400-4 1-4625-4400-2</isbn>
          <uri>https://search.ebscohost.com/login.aspx?direct=true&amp;scope=site&amp;db=nlebk&amp;db=nlabk&amp;AN=2645023</uri>
          <fpage>85</fpage>
          <lpage>105</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-hull1943">
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name><surname>Hull</surname><given-names>C. L.</given-names></name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Principles of behavior: An introduction to behavior theory</source>
          <publisher-name>Appleton-Century</publisher-name>
          <publisher-loc>Oxford, England</publisher-loc>
          <year iso-8601-date="1943">1943</year>
          <fpage>x, 422</fpage>
          <lpage></lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-kruglanski2017">
        <element-citation publication-type="webpage">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name><surname>Kruglanski</surname><given-names>Arie W.</given-names></name>
            <name><surname>Fishbach</surname><given-names>Ayelet</given-names></name>
            <name><surname>Woolley</surname><given-names>Kaitlin</given-names></name>
            <name><surname>Belanger</surname><given-names>Jocelyn</given-names></name>
            <name><surname>Chernikova</surname><given-names>Marina</given-names></name>
            <name><surname>Molinario</surname><given-names>Erica</given-names></name>
            <name><surname>Pierro</surname><given-names>Antonio</given-names></name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A Structural Model of Intrinsic Motivation: On the Psychology of Means-Ends Fusion</article-title>
          <year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.31234/osf.io/kdct8</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-kruglanski2022">
        <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name><surname>Kruglanski</surname><given-names>Arie W.</given-names></name>
            <name><surname>Molinario</surname><given-names>Erica</given-names></name>
            <name><surname>Jasko</surname><given-names>Katarzyna</given-names></name>
            <name><surname>Webber</surname><given-names>David</given-names></name>
            <name><surname>Leander</surname><given-names>N. Pontus</given-names></name>
            <name><surname>Pierro</surname><given-names>Antonio</given-names></name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Significance-Quest Theory</article-title>
          <source>Perspectives on Psychological Science</source>
          <year iso-8601-date="2022-07">2022</year><month>07</month>
          <volume>17</volume>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <issn>1745-6916, 1745-6924</issn>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/17456916211034825</pub-id>
          <fpage>1050</fpage>
          <lpage>1071</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-liden2000">
        <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name><surname>Liden</surname><given-names>Robert C.</given-names></name>
            <name><surname>Wayne</surname><given-names>Sandy J.</given-names></name>
            <name><surname>Sparrowe</surname><given-names>Raymond T.</given-names></name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>An examination of the mediating role of psychological empowerment on the relations between the job, interpersonal relationships, and work outcomes.</article-title>
          <source>Journal of Applied Psychology</source>
          <publisher-name>American Psychological Association</publisher-name>
          <year iso-8601-date="2000-06">2000</year><month>06</month>
          <volume>85</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <issn>00219010</issn>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/0021-9010.85.3.407</pub-id>
          <fpage>407</fpage>
          <lpage>416</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-perry1996">
        <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name><surname>Perry</surname><given-names>James L.</given-names></name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Measuring Public Service Motivation: An Assessment of Construct Reliability and Validity</article-title>
          <source>Journal of Public Administration Research and Theory: J-PART</source>
          <publisher-name>[Oxford University Press, Journal of Public Administration Research and Theory, Inc., Public Management Research Association]</publisher-name>
          <year iso-8601-date="1996">1996</year>
          <date-in-citation content-type="access-date"><year iso-8601-date="2024-02-27">2024</year><month>02</month><day>27</day></date-in-citation>
          <volume>6</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <issn>1053-1858</issn>
          <uri>https://www.jstor.org/stable/1181620</uri>
          <fpage>5</fpage>
          <lpage>22</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-pietryka2022">
        <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name><surname>Pietryka</surname><given-names>Matthew T.</given-names></name>
            <name><surname>MacIntosh</surname><given-names>Randall C.</given-names></name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>ANES Scales Often Do Not Measure What You Think They Measure</article-title>
          <source>The Journal of Politics</source>
          <publisher-name>The University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>
          <year iso-8601-date="2022-04">2022</year><month>04</month>
          <volume>84</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <issn>0022-3816</issn>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/715251</pub-id>
          <fpage>1074</fpage>
          <lpage>1090</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-pitts2011">
        <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name><surname>Pitts</surname><given-names>David</given-names></name>
            <name><surname>Marvel</surname><given-names>John</given-names></name>
            <name><surname>Fernandez</surname><given-names>Sergio</given-names></name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>So Hard to Say Goodbye? Turnover Intention among U.S. Federal Employees</article-title>
          <source>Public Administration Review</source>
          <publisher-name>Wiley</publisher-name>
          <year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year>
          <date-in-citation content-type="access-date"><year iso-8601-date="2024-02-27">2024</year><month>02</month><day>27</day></date-in-citation>
          <volume>71</volume>
          <issue>5</issue>
          <issn>0033-3352</issn>
          <uri>https://www.jstor.org/stable/23017442</uri>
          <fpage>751</fpage>
          <lpage>760</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-ryan2000">
        <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name><surname>Ryan</surname><given-names>Richard M.</given-names></name>
            <name><surname>Deci</surname><given-names>Edward L.</given-names></name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Intrinsic and Extrinsic Motivations: Classic Definitions and New Directions</article-title>
          <source>Contemporary Educational Psychology</source>
          <year iso-8601-date="2000-01-01">2000</year><month>01</month><day>01</day>
          <volume>25</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <issn>0361-476X</issn>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/ceps.1999.1020</pub-id>
          <fpage>54</fpage>
          <lpage>67</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-ryan2017">
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name><surname>Ryan</surname><given-names>Richard M.</given-names></name>
            <name><surname>Deci</surname><given-names>Edward L.</given-names></name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Self-determination theory : Basic psychological needs in motivation, development, and wellness</source>
          <publisher-name>Guilford Press</publisher-name>
          <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
          <year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year>
          <isbn>978-1-4625-2876-9 1-4625-2876-7 978-1-4625-3896-6 1-4625-3896-7</isbn>
          <uri>http://books.google.com/books?vid=isbn9781462528769</uri>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-ryan2021">
        <element-citation publication-type="chapter">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name><surname>Ryan</surname><given-names>Richard M.</given-names></name>
            <name><surname>Deci</surname><given-names>Edward L.</given-names></name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Human Autonomy in Social Psychology: A Self-Determination Theory Perspective</article-title>
          <source>Social psychology : Handbook of basic principles</source>
          <person-group person-group-type="editor">
            <name><surname>Lange</surname><given-names>Paul A. M. van</given-names></name>
            <name><surname>Kruglanski</surname><given-names>Arie W.</given-names></name>
          </person-group>
          <publisher-name>The Guilford Press</publisher-name>
          <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
          <year iso-8601-date="2021">2021</year>
          <edition>Third edition.</edition>
          <isbn>978-1-4625-4400-4 1-4625-4400-2</isbn>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-shapira-lishchinsky2014">
        <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name><surname>Shapira-Lishchinsky</surname><given-names>Orly</given-names></name>
            <name><surname>Tsemach</surname><given-names>Sigalit</given-names></name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Psychological Empowerment as a Mediator Between Teachers’ Perceptions of Authentic Leadership and Their Withdrawal and Citizenship Behaviors</article-title>
          <source>Educational Administration Quarterly</source>
          <publisher-name>SAGE Publications Inc</publisher-name>
          <year iso-8601-date="2014-10-01">2014</year><month>10</month><day>01</day>
          <volume>50</volume>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <issn>0013-161X</issn>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0013161X13513898</pub-id>
          <fpage>675</fpage>
          <lpage>712</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-skinner1965">
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name><surname>Skinner</surname><given-names>Burrhus Frederic</given-names></name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Science and human behavior</source>
          <publisher-name>Simon and Schuster</publisher-name>
          <year iso-8601-date="1965">1965</year>
          <isbn>0-02-929040-6</isbn>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-spreitzer1995">
        <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name><surname>Spreitzer</surname><given-names>Gretchen M.</given-names></name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Psychological Empowerment in the Workplace: Dimensions, Measurement, and Validation</article-title>
          <source>The Academy of Management Journal</source>
          <publisher-name>Academy of Management</publisher-name>
          <year iso-8601-date="1995">1995</year>
          <volume>38</volume>
          <issue>5</issue>
          <issn>0001-4273</issn>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/256865</pub-id>
          <fpage>1442</fpage>
          <lpage>1465</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-taylor2013">
        <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>Jeannette</given-names></name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Goal Setting in the Australian Public Service: Effects on Psychological Empowerment and Organizational Citizenship Behavior</article-title>
          <source>Public Administration Review</source>
          <publisher-name>Wiley</publisher-name>
          <year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year>
          <date-in-citation content-type="access-date"><year iso-8601-date="2024-02-27">2024</year><month>02</month><day>27</day></date-in-citation>
          <volume>73</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <issn>0033-3352</issn>
          <uri>https://www.jstor.org/stable/42002950</uri>
          <fpage>453</fpage>
          <lpage>464</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-tett1993">
        <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name><surname>Tett</surname><given-names>Robert P.</given-names></name>
            <name><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>John P.</given-names></name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>JOB SATISFACTION, ORGANIZATIONAL COMMITMENT, TURNOVER INTENTION, AND TURNOVER: PATH ANALYSES BASED ON META-ANALYTIC FINDINGS.</article-title>
          <source>Personnel Psychology</source>
          <year iso-8601-date="1993">1993</year>
          <volume>46</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <issn>00315826</issn>
          <uri>https://search.ebscohost.com/login.aspx?direct=true&amp;db=eue&amp;AN=9401104761&amp;site=ehost-live</uri>
          <fpage>259</fpage>
          <lpage>293</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-thomas1990">
        <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>Kenneth W.</given-names></name>
            <name><surname>Velthouse</surname><given-names>Betty A.</given-names></name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Cognitive Elements of Empowerment: An &quot;Interpretive&quot; Model of Intrinsic Task Motivation</article-title>
          <source>The Academy of Management Review</source>
          <publisher-name>Academy of Management</publisher-name>
          <year iso-8601-date="1990">1990</year>
          <volume>15</volume>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <issn>0363-7425</issn>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/258687</pub-id>
          <fpage>666</fpage>
          <lpage>681</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-gardner2000">
        <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name><surname>Gardner</surname><given-names>Wendi L.</given-names></name>
            <name><surname>Pickett</surname><given-names>Cynthia L.</given-names></name>
            <name><surname>Brewer</surname><given-names>Marilynn B.</given-names></name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Social Exclusion and Selective Memory: How the Need to belong Influences Memory for Social Events</article-title>
          <source>Personality and Social Psychology Bulletin</source>
          <year iso-8601-date="2000-04-01">2000</year><month>04</month><day>01</day>
          <volume>26</volume>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <uri>https://doi.org/10.1177/0146167200266007</uri>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0146167200266007</pub-id>
          <fpage>486</fpage>
          <lpage>496</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-mcleod2022">
        <element-citation>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name><surname>Mcleod</surname><given-names>Saul</given-names></name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Maslow’s hierarchy of needs</article-title>
          <year iso-8601-date="2022-11-03">2022</year><month>11</month><day>03</day>
          <uri>https://www.simplypsychology.org/maslow.html</uri>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </sec>
</sec>
</body>

<back>
<fn-group>
  <fn id="fn1">
    <label>1</label><p>Note that “generalized expectations of control”
    here simply refers to self-reported educational attainment on a
    7-point scale.</p>
  </fn>
  <fn id="fn2">
    <label>2</label><p>Note that this is the same reasoning explicated
    in procedural theories of representative democracy, though under
    different predicate assumptions
    (<xref alt="Dahl 1961" rid="ref-dahl1961" ref-type="bibr">Dahl
    1961</xref>;
    <xref alt="Dahl and Shapiro 2015" rid="ref-dahl2015" ref-type="bibr">Dahl
    and Shapiro 2015</xref>).</p>
  </fn>
  <fn id="fn3">
    <label>3</label><p>From Ashforth’s study, it’s unclear exactly which
    variables are the dependent versus the independent variables, but it
    is clear that the primary variable of interest, powerlessness, is
    the independent variable of most importance to the author.
    Powerlessness, however, was measured by a combination of five
    different subscale measures derived from multiple sources, one of
    which included 32 survey items. The measurement of powerlessness was
    assessed by a combination of 1) the 3-item Job Autonomy Scale from
    the Job Diagnostics Survey
    (<xref alt="Hackman and Oldham 1974" rid="ref-hackman1974" ref-type="bibr">Hackman
    and Oldham 1974</xref>,
    <xref alt="1975" rid="ref-hackman1975" ref-type="bibr">1975</xref>),
    2) the 4-item Job Authority scale from the revised Organizational
    Assessment Instrument, 3) self-reported job grade, 4) ratings of
    autonomy and participation (based on job title) by one job
    evaluation specialist, 5) a 32-item Powerlessness scale which
    consisted of a 15-item Participation subscale and a 17-item Autonomy
    subscale. It is not entirely clear where the 32-item powerlessness
    scale is adapted from.</p>
  </fn>
  <fn id="fn4">
    <label>4</label><p>Note that in the article cited, no test of the
    theoretical model is included, and no empirical results presented to
    validate the model. Instead, the authors rely on references to
    literature from psychology and clinical researchers. The abstract of
    the cited article mentions preliminary evidence that substantiates
    it, but the preliminary evidence mentioned in the abstract is
    confined to brief summaries of two different studies near the end of
    the article, where the evidence described suggests support for the
    authors interpretive model of empowerment. Thus, the review article
    argues for a particular non-traditional paradigm of management which
    fosters a worker’s empowerment in theory.</p>
  </fn>
  <fn id="fn5">
    <label>5</label><p>The attempt to understand empowerment as
    “intrinsic task motivation” did not stick in the long run, but the
    multidimensional nature of the construct, as well as the four
    essential components, did.</p>
  </fn>
  <fn id="fn6">
    <label>6</label><p>Autonomy, in the framework of Self-Determination
    Theory, refers to the need to experience volition by controlling
    one’s own behavior such that it integrates with one’s sense of self,
    and the experience of autonomy depends on the degree to which a
    person’s behavior is motivated by the level of external control
    versus the intrinsic motivation (for review see
    <xref alt="Higgins and Nakkawita 2021" rid="ref-higgins2021" ref-type="bibr">Higgins
    and Nakkawita 2021</xref>).</p>
  </fn>
  <fn id="fn7">
    <label>7</label><p>The evidence the authors cite to are two
    unpublished doctoral dissertations. The description of the two
    studies suggests that these dissertations were directly testing the
    cognitive model of empowerment they introduce in their review.
    However, these studies were unable to be located for direct
    citation.</p>
  </fn>
  <fn id="fn8">
    <label>8</label><p>See online appendix for additional notes on
    measurement for the scale.</p>
  </fn>
  <fn id="fn9">
    <label>9</label><p>Organizational Citizenship Behavior is defined
    differently by different scholars, but is best understood as
    voluntary work behavior done within an organization that is not
    required as part of the worker’s duties of employment. It is a
    blanket term that refers to worker behavior that contributes benefit
    to the organization but is beyond their formal obligations.</p>
  </fn>
  <fn id="fn10">
    <label>10</label><p>See online appendix for expanded scrutiny of the
    latter two articles cited.</p>
  </fn>
  <fn id="fn11">
    <label>11</label><p>OCBI : “I help others who have heavy workloads”,
    “I take time to listen to co-workers’ problems and worries”. “I go
    out of my way to help new employees.” “I assist my supervisor with
    his/her work even when I am not asked.”</p>
  </fn>
  <fn id="fn12">
    <label>12</label><p>OCBO: “My attendance at work is above the norm”,
    “I obey informal rules that maintain order”, “I give advance notice
    when I am unable to work”</p>
  </fn>
  <fn id="fn13">
    <label>13</label><p>Goal-difficulty: “A high degree of skill and
    know-how is necessary to do my job well.”, “Jobs like mine are quite
    demanding day after day.”</p>
  </fn>
  <fn id="fn14">
    <label>14</label><p>Goal-specificity: “My responsibilities at work
    are very clear and specific.”, “I understand fully which of my job
    duties are more important than others.”</p>
  </fn>
  <fn id="fn15">
    <label>15</label><p>“Authentic leadership” was measured using four
    survey items: “My principal says exactly what he or she means”, “My
    principal admits to mistakes when they are made”, “My principal
    tells me the hard truth”, and “My principal outwardly displays how
    she/he feels”. (See Appendix in
    <xref alt="Shapira-Lishchinsky and Tsemach 2014" rid="ref-shapira-lishchinsky2014" ref-type="bibr">Shapira-Lishchinsky
    and Tsemach 2014</xref>)</p>
  </fn>
  <fn id="fn16">
    <label>16</label><p>Q58 from the Federal Human Capital Survey
    (FHCS): “How do you rate the amount of pay you get on your job?”
    (1=very poor…5=very good).</p>
  </fn>
  <fn id="fn17">
    <label>17</label><p>The dependent variables–turnout intention to
    leave agency and turnout intention to leave government–are derived
    from the same survey item question, “Are you considering leaving
    your organization within the next year, and if so, why?” How the
    authors are able to create two variables from one question with a
    dichotomous response of yes or no is beyond me. They don’t state
    that the Federal Human Capital Survey in 2006 asks the question
    twice for both agency and government turnover intentions, so the
    reader is left to presume such is the case.</p>
  </fn>
  <fn id="fn18">
    <label>18</label><p>Pay satisfaction was measured with a single-item
    on a 5-point Likert scale: “Considering everything, how satisfied
    are you with your pay?”</p>
  </fn>
  <fn id="fn19">
    <label>19</label><p>Benefits satisfaction was measured with three
    items on a 5-point Likert scale: “How satisfied are you with
    retirement benefits?”, “How satisfied are you with health insurance
    benefits?”, “How satisfied are you with life insurance
    benefits?”</p>
  </fn>
  <fn id="fn20">
    <label>20</label><p>Advancement Opportunity Satisfaction was
    measured with a single-item on a 5-point Likert scale: “How
    satisfied are you with your opportunity to get a better job in your
    organization?”</p>
  </fn>
  <fn id="fn21">
    <label>21</label><p>Job satisfaction was measured with a single-item
    on a 5-point Likert scale: “Considering everything, how satisfied
    are you with your job?”</p>
  </fn>
  <fn id="fn22">
    <label>22</label><p>Pitts, Marvel, and Fernandez
    (<xref alt="2011" rid="ref-pitts2011" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>)
    don’t specify the number of observations explicitly. Rather, the
    number of observations in the survey is found in Table 2 on page 755
    (<inline-formula><alternatives>
    <tex-math><![CDATA[n = 217,504]]></tex-math>
    <mml:math display="inline" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>217</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>504</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>).
    From the cumulative percentages of those indicating turnover,
    whether leaving agency or government, that amounts to about
    <inline-formula><alternatives>
    <tex-math><![CDATA[42,848]]></tex-math>
    <mml:math display="inline" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>42</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>848</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>
    employees from the sample who reported an intention to leave within
    the next year (assuming my math is correct). The count of those who
    reported intention to leave an agency but stay working within
    federal government is approximately <inline-formula><alternatives>
    <tex-math><![CDATA[35,018]]></tex-math>
    <mml:math display="inline" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>35</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>018</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>.
    Whereas the approximate count of those who reported intention to
    leave federal government work overall is
    <inline-formula><alternatives>
    <tex-math><![CDATA[7,830]]></tex-math>
    <mml:math display="inline" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>7</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>830</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>.
    Seeing as how leaving government is far less substantial a figure
    than leaving an agency, I see the reason for the distinction between
    the two but it would have been better to include an actual turnover
    rate of some sort for the past year at least. A statistic from the
    Bureau of Labor Statistics, or some other concurrent figure that
    demonstrates just how significant turnover actually is for
    government employees. The authors mention some consistent 20 year
    decline, but don’t present the evidence of that.</p>
  </fn>
</fn-group>
</back>



</article>